Welcome to the talk on automatic code
performance with AI.
So, we all love our code to run really
fast, but it usually seems like we are
always under pressure to uh make the
feature work and just ship it quickly.
We just never really get the time to
optimize our code fully. So, today I I
am going to talk about how we can think
of the first version uh the first
working version as the spec itself, and
then how AI can help us make our code
run faster with AI.
Um
and while preserving correctness and
then making it all automated.
So, uh I can start by introducing
myself. So, I'm Saurabh, the founder and
CEO of Code Flash.
So, um I grew up in India, but currently
live in San Francisco. So, I have around
8 years of experience in software
engineering and machine learning. And I
have built performance tools at Nvidia
where chip architects would use it to
figure out how they could optimize the
GPUs themselves.
And I have um led ML at Cresta, built ML
models and gen AI models at Meta.
So, all this while I've been really uh
passionate about writing performant code
and optimizing them.
So, um I wanted to start with talking
about how higher-level dynamic languages
have taken over the world.
Um in particular, Python, JavaScript,
TypeScript are the top languages right
now.
And I think that's because it's most
loved by developers and it's the easiest
to develop new software in. So, you can
quickly ship new software with these
languages.
But then, let's focus on the number one
language over here. And let me be
slightly controversial and say that
Python has won.
So, Python uh is leading the AI
revolution right now. And uh so, this
talk will give some love to Python and
then talk about performance optimization
with Python as an example language. But
the general concepts we are going to
talk about in this presentation will
apply to all the other languages as
well.
So, so why We all know Python is
awesome, but why do developers like it?
It's very readable code. Um Python has
English
uh keywords. It has like line breaks for
visually distinct code. It makes it easy
to read. It's very portable. You can
write one Python code somewhere and then
like be uh make Python makes it really
easy that it can can write once and make
it run everywhere.
And then, it also has a large number of
libraries. So, you can literally
if you start uh solving a standard
problem, there's probably a library that
has already solved it for you. So, you
can directly just go and use it.
It's also default language for data
science and ML. There's tons of
libraries available like Pandas, NumPy,
PyTorch, TensorFlow that use uh
Python to do the work.
And then, most importantly, like it
leads to higher developer productivity.
So, developers love it because it allows
developers to do a lot more with very
few lines of code. And that's what makes
them highly productive.
But when I think about this from a
performance standpoint, like these
awesome features can also make Python
really slow.
Um
readability means that interpreter has
to convert all that human-readable code
into machine instructions. And in
Python, it happens during runtime, which
can make it really slow.
Um
Also, it's portable, but when I think
about it, I think that, "Hey, you know
what? Python may not be using all the
available machine instructions fully.
So, it might get slower."
Um it has a large number of libraries.
So, we might not actually know what
their performance might be because there
are so many of them, right? So, it's
hard to make decisions on performance
with respect to that.
So, most of the data science and ML
libraries are actually compiled code.
But then still, because we are using
Python, like Python itself can become
the bottleneck with performance.
And then, high developer productivity,
what that leads to is this culture of
shipping quickly, making sure that um
things work. And once they work, you
just test it and then just ship it to
production and move on.
The problem over here is that uh
developers may not prioritize
uh performance enough.
Because the way Python, the language
itself is, it can hard to understand
what might be performant in Python
versus what's not.
So, let's just like think about this for
a bit. And then, I have this
question for all of you. Like which
statement amongst the two would run
faster in Python?
So, the first one um is initializing two
variables like X and Y with two integers
in Python.
Uh and you're doing a sum operation on
that. And the second one, there's a two
floating points in Python and these are
double precision in Python. And you
again like do a sum on them. So, for the
sum operation,
uh which one do you think is faster?
And I can't access the chat, but
So, I'll I'll I'll jump in. I'll jump
in. I think there's a slight there's a
slight delay on the chat of around 10
seconds. So, while people while people
are adding that, I'm going to have to
say the faster one has to be the integer
one. Cuz I mean, I know floating points
take that much longer to do anything
with. So, I'd go I'd go integer.
I mean, that's what I thought as well.
But then, the problem is that
performance uh in Python turns out
actually the floating point, the double
precision is faster in Python than
integer addition.
And that uh just like drives the point
across that performance can get slightly
hard to reason about in Python.
Because like the reason over here is
that integers are not actually really
32-bit or 40 uh 64-bit integers in
Python. These are Python objects and
integers in Python can be of any length
essentially. So, there is some overhead
involved in like handling all of that.
So, that just makes like integer
addition slower than even like floating
point addition in Python.
So, so there's there's like complexity
with uh performance in Python.
But then, with this being said,
performance today is mostly a neglected
endeavor
that developers only get to when things
get really slow.
Um so, one of the key reasons why uh
performance usually get neglected today
is because just developers don't have
sufficient time to make sure that all
the applications are fast.
So, most of them are under pressure to
ship new features like and then go to
all the backlog they have.
So, they just like make sure that it
works and they ship it quickly without
giving much thought about whether it can
be optimized. And that leads to slower
applications.
Um
And I think that's also true because it
just takes time to optimize, right? So,
and also, moreover, performance
optimizations require experience and
usually deep domain expertise to really
understand how everything is working
and uh make it all performant. It
requires going deep into like this the
the the system itself, like the
algorithms, like how things may be
interacting with each other.
And yeah, and then then finding a new
more efficient way of doing the same
thing.
Um it requires a ton of skill sometimes.
And then, the whole process is like
manual, tedious, and time-consuming.
Um
So, when you have deadline to hit, uh
you need to do to If you wanted to do
performance optimization, you need to
create a benchmark. So, figure out some
like end-to-end workflow that you want
to speed up.
And then profile it to find some
hotspots. And then basically after that,
it becomes like a
game of creativity of the developer. The
developer then has to figure out, "Hey,
could this same thing be done in a
better manner?" And it goes into like a
a deep research at this moment. And then
the programmer comes up with few ideas
and then
applies those ideas and sees, "Hey, is
this Did this actually break the code or
is this even faster?"
And this has happened with me when you
like have deep into some optimizations
uh after
hours or days and then the optimized
code just runs slower
than the original one.
Uh and this uh sometimes makes me give
up on optimization, but carry on.
Um so, this is just to say that
performance optimization is like can be
problematic in practice to do
because there's like other things to do
as well.
So,
this leads to the world we are today
where software can be a lot slower than
the highest possible efficient version
of it.
And then like we have users complaining,
the costs go up, all of those problems.
So,
let's think about how we can solve this.
So, I think this is like how the future
of software development will evolve.
So, so developers will be responsible
for the behavioral specification of the
software.
I think the week also covered this in
like
the keynote today where um
uh guy was talking about specs,
spec-driven development. But like the
way I think about specs right now is
think of the first implementation you
have where things work as the spec
itself.
Um
And so, developers will be responsible
for the spec of the of the program.
Um
So, and AI will help with the first
implementation. So, in a co-pilot style
fashion as we have today,
uh AI will make sure that we can get to
the first working version quickly.
But then, moreover, AI will now
automatically handle the non-functional
requirements for us. Things like
security,
uh knowing if there are bugs, fixing it,
deployment, like making sure it's
deployed automatically,
reducing the cost of the application,
and even performance over here.
So, so now I I we will focus on how
performance can be automated
since developers
in practice don't or can't spend so much
time on performance. It would be great
if AI could automate this thing.
So, I'm here to tell you that this will
not just happen in the future, but is
reality today.
So, yeah, let me show you how CodeFlash
actually works and how we can actually
automate any new code we're going to
write.
So, this is a live demo, so I'm just
like going to pull request over here.
And right before the presentation, I
just like pushed some changes.
I'm going to choose the right base
branch and then just create a new pull
request.
So,
so here's the code I just pushed.
I had like this
uh this code in here, simple code, just
like finds common tags between the list
of articles.
And uh there's this like tag thing. And
then basically loops through all the
other articles and like basically does
an intersection between all of them. So,
it figures out if the new common tags
are the same as previous common tags and
updates it. And basically returns a set
of common tags.
Seems simple enough. And because I'm
good good programmer, I also like to
write tests.
I just wrote these two test cases. So,
here's how the input looks like. It has
a title, has some tags.
And then between these three, Python and
AI are the common tags. This is like
what I assert.
Basically I do test cases for it.
That's all that. So, in my code base, I
actually have CodeFlash installed here
already.
So, CodeFlash will now read this code
and then will try to optimize it.
Let's see what happens. So, the way
CodeFlash works is it sets up your
Python environment, it installs all the
pip dependencies, like just the way you
would install your project. And then
CodeFlash starts executing.
So, the way CodeFlash works is it like
finds this like one function to optimize
in the current git diff. And then
discovers all the existing unit tests
you may have in your uh in your repo.
So, it discovered 361 existing unit
tests.
Um and then it found this function to
optimize.
All fair and well.
And then after that, uh wait a second.
Um it starts it discovered this one test
file we just committed. And then starts
generating new tests for it and new
optimizations for it.
It generated two test files for it and
generated four optimizations for it.
And here are here are how the tests look
like.
And then basically what happens is we
now started running the original code to
figure out what the what is the behavior
for it.
So, we run all the tests. So, the two
test cases we wrote passed. 31 new
generated tests passed.
And the original code runtime was 774
milliseconds. That's what we
benchmarked.
And here's the first candidate, first
optimization. So, we don't really know
if it's correct or not, so we run all
the tests again and then all of the same
cases passed, which is great. So, all
the test results passed and it this is
like 90x faster because it runs in 8.4
milliseconds.
Um the second one, this is the this is
how it looks like. This is also correct,
but it's 90x faster, sort of very
similar.
The third one, um this is 90x faster,
like again very similar.
Um the fourth one is 34x faster and the
test results passed. So, we figured out
the fastest one, which is still correct,
generate explanations and everything.
And go back and create the suggestion
back in the PR.
So, here's how CodeFlash suggested it.
It says, "You know what? If you were to
instead of using all this, you can use
initialize it as a set
and use this dot intersection update
function over sets.
That takes in a list and quickly updates
it.
And yeah, if if you don't have any
common tags, you can just break early."
Cool. So, it like says, "You know what?
This made it 90x faster. Runtime went
from 774 milliseconds to 8.4
milliseconds." Explains why is this
faster.
It shows you here, "You know what? All
the tests passed, all the generated
tests passed." And so, it did like its
best to figure out the behavior is same.
And now
I feel it's good, I just go and commit
the changes.
So, yeah, it basically shows you that it
like does all the work in the
background. Like you can ship all the
changes you have and then let CodeFlash
run as a CI check.
And then it can automatically optimize
all the code it can optimize.
So, yeah. Um
So, that was the demo.
But then going back,
so the question may be that, "Hey, you
know what?
That code seemed simple. Like what is it
really practical? Like what type of
optimizations can CodeFlash automate?"
Um
Yeah, so
it can actually help you find and
discover better algorithms for your
code. So,
over here, like this is like a LangChain
example we merged.
So, the function was cosine similarity
top K.
And basically the the way it works is
you have two matrices, X and Y.
And you do row-wise
cosine similarity between the two
matrices.
Something like Cartesian product.
And then you figure out the top K
the indices with the top K
cosine similarity numbers, so like
highest ones.
The original implementation was like do
a sort over all of them. And then find
the top K and then like do some indexing
over here.
So,
with like big matrices, like if you have
1,000,
uh the number of the array can be 1,000
squared, which is like large numbers, n
squared type of a behavior. So, what
CodeFlash said, "Hey, you know what?
Instead of that, you can use this
argpartition function in NumPy."
So, argpartition is like the quicksort
pivot
uh operation where you can like get all
the top K elements before and all the
smaller ones later.
And then you can only sort the top K
ones. That's all. That makes it like
much faster. You don't have to do extra
work. And then this got merged into
LangChain, uh sped it up by 148%.
Another example, it can it CodeFlash can
actually suggest better libraries to
use.
So, I mean we all use JSON in Python,
but turns out there's a better library
called ORJSON in Python.
And this optimization sped up this code
for 70%
uh by by 70% for Airbyte.
So, and this was automatically uh
discovered.
It can simplify compute for you. So,
so this is like some operations over
data frame.
So, if the data So, basically figuring
out if is there any nulls in the data
frame and this was originally
implemented as this.
So, you're doing two sums across two
axes. Uh it's like expensive operation.
So, if this can be simplified as this.
Just access all the values and use a dot
any operation in here. So, this like
sped this up by 433%.
And it can actually also find more um
exotic types of optimizations. So,
um recursion can get really expensive
sometimes if you're going really deep
recursions uh because recursion you have
to create the whole call stack and
everything and this can get specially
expensive in Python.
So, it said, "Hey, you know what?
Instead of doing this deep recursion
like here, you can use a stack yourself
and then like
append items to it and then pop from
it." And basically do this like in a
loop over here.
So, this does not need any function
calls. And this sped up Pydantic by
about 34% for like JSON ref parser.
Other than that, I mean what I've seen
is like it actually fixes a bunch of
performance mistakes we make. This is
actually my code I wrote like last week
where um
So, think of it as like adding to some
dictionary type of a data structure.
And what I wanted to figure out is that,
"Hey,
is does it is is this key already
present in that? And if it's present,
then like throw a warning. Should not
happen. But if it's not present, then
create a new key and then like give this
uh value."
But then the problem I made was that I
called this function twice.
Simple mistake. So, simple optimization
over here was that, "Hey, you know what?
Just call it once, save it in variable
and use it everywhere."
So, this was in a inner loop for
CodeFlash, like sped CodeFlash up by 40%
for this operation.
Um
Also, one of the other mistakes people
make is you don't So, this was another
code in Pydantic where if each name
validators was false,
you the original code would still like
do a lot of processing and then it
eventually return schema. So, it figured
out that, "Hey, you know what? If you or
actually early exit, you can make it
much faster in this case." And that
actually led to a 100% speed up for
Pydantic.
It's quite cool.
So, so CodeFlash um can still find a lot
of other types of optimizations, but
it still can't find many of the types
yet and we're always optimi- uh
improving it, but the good thing is that
it's like a general purpose optimizer
now. Like whatever Python code you throw
to it, it can usually do a really good
job at figuring out the figuring out the
best version of it.
And it uh does not just optimize it, it
also ensures correctness and does
everything. Like the whole
the whole process that an engineer would
do is like what CodeFlash does
automatically.
So, the best thing about CodeFlash is
that we can do this at scale.
Um so, since CodeFlash is essentially
just a software,
it does not require human attention to
figure out, "Hey, could this be made
faster?" Doing the whole thing about
performance optimization.
Um we can now start to optimize any
Python code base. And it this is like
what we do quite frequently. We just
like download a package, run CodeFlash
on it, usually finds a bunch of
optimizations we like contribute to open
source right now with this. By the way,
you can try this as well.
So, yeah, I mean so with this, we can't
we can optimize all existing code, but
also any new code we are writing. So, we
install CodeFlash as a uh GitHub
optimizer as you saw.
And then we can implement continuous
optimization on our code bases to make
sure like all the future code we write
is fast as well.
So, I think with that, I think I'm going
to uh talk a bit about like how
CodeFlash works and like how the
principles behind like AI-based
performance optimization.
So, this like basically breaks down to
three problems. Like first is generating
optimization candidates, like basically
generating the optimizations themselves.
Second one is correctness testing,
knowing if this new code we generated,
is that even correct? And then
benchmarking the performance, like
knowing is this even faster or is this
just a use?
So, so So, for generating optimization,
what we usually do is we understand the
whole repository, we know where the
tests are, where all the functions are,
all the linkages everywhere.
And then we figure out the code context
for a particular code we're optimizing,
fetch it all from everywhere, and put it
to a LLM-based optimization model.
And the optimization model says, "Hey,
you know what? Maybe this is a way to
speed it up. Maybe that is a way to
speed it up." It tries a bunch of ideas.
Some may be good, some may not be, so
it's it cannot be certain about it, but
it tries its best.
Um so, after that, what we do is we
the other important problem we solve is
correctness uh verification.
So, we don't want to like merge in a
code that breaks our code, right?
So, so we want the new code to behave
exactly the same way as the original
code.
So, if we were to swap the original code
out with the new code in, it should
behave exactly the same way, right?
So, it's a hard problem, but the way we
solve it is by
generating a bunch of inputs to the uh
to the original function,
and then um executing the both the
original and the
optimized code with both of them,
and then seeing, "Hey, how did it
behave?"
Uh so, for example, for for a given
input, like what was the output in terms
of like all the all the behavioral
specs.
And then make sure that the behavior for
both the versions are exactly equal.
So, that's that. Um and the way we
generate inputs is by variety of
techniques.
We discover all the existing unit tests
you may have. We generate a bunch of new
LLM-generated tests.
Um we can trace ex-
workflows end to end and figure out,
"Hey, what were the inputs to specific
parts of the program?" And generate
replay tests.
We have some more like exotic concolic
tests as well.
So, with this, like we can run tens or
hundreds of inputs,
and then um
to ensure that the two functions we have
are actually equivalent.
So, we can't definitely prove that they
are equivalent, but practically we can
come very close to knowing that these
are actually equivalent.
So, um
and the last step is actually just
benchmarking performance. This can also
get quite tricky with general-purpose
code.
And the way this usually works is by
generating a diverse performance
benchmark. So, knowing that, "Hey, you
know what? Um
for all these different inputs, here's
how the performance behaves, and the the
runtime behaves."
And we auto-instrument code to measure
runtimes, and then we also implement
some of the best practices in in
benchmarking itself by looping the code
many times to find stable runtimes. Um
we denoise the measured runtime,
and all of that.
Um so, yeah, I mean, with this we know
with a very high confidence if the new
code is indeed faster.
So, that's like the basics. So, I mean,
with this you now know the basics of
automated performance optimizers with
AI.
Yeah, I think that's basically all I
had. So, just wanted to say that I think
you should adopt automated code
optimization
in your software engineering workflow.
So, this helps you always write fast and
expert-level code.
And we have seen like our users, when
they adopt Codeflash, uh
see significant speedups in the in the
software they build.
And this also makes them change the way
they write the code. So, uh with this,
like you don't really have to think
about, "Hey, is this the best way you
could have written something?"
You you can just focus on, "Is this
working? Is this correct?" And then like
basically offload the optimization to
AI. So, this way we have seen like our
users be more productive.
So, yeah, I mean, that's all about
Codeflash. Like it's quite simple to
install right now. You can use it today
on your Python projects with this like
pip install Codeflash.
Um we have a Discord channel. Like join
us if you're interested in this field,
and then you want to try it out. Uh it's
also free, by the way. You can try it
out as much as you want right now.
Um yeah.
And then feel free to follow me. I'm
happy to uh
speak more about like principles behind
it. And also, by the way, we are hiring.
So, if you're interested in like
building this with us, I I will happy to
talk to you. Yeah, that's all.
Um amazing. Thank you, Saurabh. Um and
I'll leave I'll leave this slide on just
cuz there's a number of a number of
links there as well. We have some
questions that are popping into the
chat. Thank you very much. Um I think I
think your talk really resonated with
people. It was definitely the right
level because uh there's a lot of
interesting comments that are appearing
in the chat. Um why don't we go ahead
and let's have a look. Why don't we
start this one from this this this this
person called Guy Pajani. I'm not I'm
not sure if that's how I if that's how I
if I said it right, Guy, or not. He says
he loves the AI optimization use case,
but how good are the LLMs at these
optimizations compared to new code gen?
Any opinions on specific models, which
is another interesting part of that
question cuz of course
people are people are finding that
certain models are better at different
tasks.
Yeah, I think
this was like the interesting the the
aha moment for me was like when GPT-4
came out, and I realized that, "Holy
it's really good at optimization."
And it's only getting better. So, what I
can say is that like for current LLM
models are really good at optimization.
But what we have seen is like
it can only generate optimization
candidates, as I like to say it. Um it
can it can say, "Hey, this is might
Maybe this is fast. Hey, maybe that is
fast." And that's the problem where you
may not really know if it's Is it
actually correct or did it just break
the code? Or is it actually fast or is
it actually even faster? So, you need to
have to do this whole benchmarking and
everything. I think that's like the
crucial piece over here. And I think
there's like levels to it as well. So,
um you can increase the complexity and
difficulty of how much you want to
optimize.
At At the limiting case, you can think
of like throwing a whole code base, and
it like re-architects everything, makes
everything fast. I don't think we are
there yet. Maybe one day, or maybe
there's like some things we can do.
But I think what I was would say that
models are like pretty good at
optimization right now. The good thing
is that
I think like from a
perspective or like theoretical
perspective, I think it's easier problem
for code uh LLM to optimize it because
if you think about like
the information you give to an LLM in a
prompt, it's just a "Hey, build me a
tic-tac-toe" or something, right? That's
like very ill-defined problem. Like with
optimization, you give an original first
working version code as prompt, right?
And that's very well specified, very
well defined. You can run it, you can do
all sorts of all sorts of things like
over there, right? So, what I would say
is from a difficulty level, it's
probably easier.
As an op- uh optimization isn't probably
an easier problem for LLMs than
uh just like zero-shot uh application
generation.
Yeah, awesome. A couple of other
questions actually based on that. In
fact, what do we jump to um Orry first,
and then we'll um and maybe Macy after
that, and then we'll jump back to Kevin.
Um Orry asks, "Adding to Guy's question,
what's the rate of false positives or
false negatives uh on that as well?"
That's a good question. So, that's like
something we focus on quite a lot. So,
false positives um usually what what
they mean is that something like
Codeflash finds an optimization where
it's actually not an optimization. Mhm.
So, that's something we like work on
quite a lot to make sure it's very low.
And we have gotten really really good
right now, by the way. So, it usually
boils down to testing a lot of cases,
making sure that um and like real-world
code can get really complex.
So, it means um
um
covering a lot more of the input space,
and then like doing coverage analysis.
Um and like that's why we have like four
five types of testing. We going to add
one more to one more type of testing
soon.
And then um
also benchmarking very effectively.
So, knowing making sure that, "Hey, you
know what? Are we actually really
faster, or was it just like system
noise?"
And real-world programs can have side
effects. They can do network calls. They
can do database queries. That makes
things harder. So, what I would say is
that I think like this question
basically brings down to just boils down
to just testing it more thoroughly. And
I think like with this empirical
testing, you can't in a from a
theoretical perspective, you can't get
to 100%
uh correctness. And that's just like
open question computer sciences, but you
can get really really close.
The more you test.
Awesome.
Uh and then I'll I'll
follow up with Macy's question, and then
we'll go back to Kevin's, as I
mentioned. Uh Macy asks, "What is the
hardest part of making this work? Is it
figuring out what the optimization is?
Is it figuring out if it actually is
faster? Um making sure it's not going to
regress anything? Or is it And you've
got a cop out here. Is it all of the
above?"
I mean, true. I think so.
Like I think the like the way I like to
talk talk to new candidates is like this
is the hardest problem I've solved.
Uh it's super hard. It's uh
quite exciting as well, by the way.
What I would say actually is like the
optimization is the easier part,
mhm uh
funnily enough. So, you can throw like
even today, you can like throw some
random code to ChatGPT, it will like do
a good job at it.
But like automating it requires
elevating it to a whole new standard.
Right. And that's where I think like the
hardest part right now is like
verification of correctness.
That's super hard. Like even like
practically speaking, benchmarking was
super hard because like you run on a VM,
even system noise is pretty hard. Like
we have had a lot of false positives
that way, and we have now gotten really
really good. So, now we like loop
hundreds of thousands of times and then
figure out like stable run time from
that. So, that
is is cool. I mean,
uh it's quite hard, but now it works.
So, I'm happy.
Yeah.
Um
following that, let's get let's jump to
Kevin uh Kevin's question now. Um you
said that it optimized Pedantic by 100%.
Um does that mean that CodeFlash is
opening PRs that are being accepted in
real-world projects?
Yeah, I mean 100%. So, we already have
like
people using us in their production
workflows. So,
I think you can actually scan like a So,
like the the way we optimize Pedantic is
like just download Pedantic, set up
CodeFlash and run this CodeFlash
all command. Mhm. So, basically
it like scans the whole repository and
tries to optimize every part of code
over there. And it like usually creates
like tens of PRs that way. Yeah.
So, yeah. I mean, that way we just like
Pedantic wanted to improve improve
improve the performance. So, we just
like did that, merged I think 12 or 12
PRs into them. So, yeah. They are being
accepted. Yeah, what
on top of that, how do you find cuz
obviously my previous roles at Snyk, um
so we obviously used to raise a a ton of
PRs where needed against security
components and things like that. How did
you find um when PRs were being created,
how did you find that developer almost
um
that that willingness to accept those
PRs when there's always a cost of you
know, doing work on any PR that gets
created. Do do you find that you know,
developers are are happy to take that on
because they see a value in that
improvement of performance or are they
more hesitant?
I think I would say
developers are generally
in hesitant, uh especially from like
AI-written code.
Um especially when it claims to be like,
you know what, I have solved this
problem. They're like, "Hey, are you
really sure?" So, that happens, but that
basically just means that the standards
are higher over here. Yes. So, I think
the way we try to uh solve that is by
doing a lot more work than what a
developer might have done himself.
Mhm.
So, we generate like tens or hundreds of
test cases and a developer might just
write three or five cases.
And then we do a lot of benchmarking
very rigorously. We like do a lot more
analysis to make make sure that we are
testing is testing it correctly and it
does not break the code and do a lot of
things. So, I think that just means that
the bar for accepting and is higher.
Yeah, that I think that's what it's like
that cost of change, isn't it? And it's
like that ability to have that trust in
the PR is huge to accept and try. Um we
have a couple more couple more minutes
or minute. Let's try and let's go We've
got two two more questions left. So,
hopefully there won't be any more. If
there is, uh please please go to the
Discord uh chat and we can continue our
conversation there well beyond the
conference. Uh Sarthak asks, is it
handling um optimization of
non-deterministic behavior of codebases
as well?
Wow, I love these questions. I would say
probably
not, but it depends. So, okay. So, if if
if
someone asks CodeFlash to optimize a
random number generator,
I don't think we can optimize it because
like function is truly random. You can't
know if the function behavior is still
the same. So, I would say no and for
that, but for a lot of other things, you
can actually
make non-deterministic functions
deterministic. So, for example, you have
like a datetime.now function.
Um you can literally like patch the
library to always return a constant now
string, for example. That way you can
make it deterministic. And then like you
can have a random number generator a
random integer generator and you can
like seed that before this. So, we can
like handle some of the non-determinism,
but in the limiting case, we can't
handle all of it.
Got it. Okay. And to the last question,
uh Farhat asks, does CodeFlash have
access to the web for the latest
libraries? For example, if a new library
um that was five times faster
uh oh, sorry. I I accidentally clicked
something there. There we go. That was
five times faster than alternatives came
out tomorrow, do you have to manually
add it? And I always troll the
JavaScript community. So, let's assume
this is in this is similar to the
JavaScript community where a new library
comes out every 10 to 20 seconds. Um can
CodeFlash uh access all those latest and
greatest?
I mean, I think so like we solve the
problem by not solving it sol- solving
it in a way. We empirically validate the
performance. So, imagine that like
you're working on some library version
two, library version three comes out.
Um we literally test the performance
with that. And we see, "Hey, is it
actually faster or not?" So, we don't
make any assumptions because performance
is very dependent on the context on your
workload. So, we literally run your
workload and see is it actually faster?
And if it is faster, then we create the
PR.
Right. Do you do you automatically pick
up that that third version is available
and try and and and make that assumption
that it is or is there work manually
that you have to do within CodeFlash to
kind of like work that out?
So, right now I think we don't directly
upgrade the library version because that
would mess up the Python environment
itself. And I think it's probably future
work for us. But I think we can like do,
hey, use uh instead of Python lists, for
example, use NumPy. Yeah. Those type of
optimizations we can make, um but
uh installing new libraries can get
slightly hard because you're messing up
with the whole environment. But that's
definitely possible.
Awesome.
Saurabh, thank you very, very much for
for the session. It was very insightful
and you can tell by the number of
questions it really resonated with our
audience. So, very, very much appreciate
you supporting our conference and thank
you for the session uh that you gave.
Thank you very much.